Finding Aid for Michigan Technology Council
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Technology Council records 1968-1987, 1978-1983
Michigan Technology Council.
2 linear feet
9722 Bimu 2
Statewide organization based a the University of Michigan to promote cooperation between industry and educational institutions and to encourage industrial and economic development in Michigan. Records include correspondence, minutes of meetings, topical files and reports.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection (Accession No. 5993. ) were received through J. Downs Herold of the University of Michigan Institute for Science and Technology in 1992.
The collection is open for research.
The Michigan Technology Council began in October 1978 as an ad hoc coalition of representatives from the University of Michigan, technology-based industries, and the Ann Arbor Chamber of Commerce. Originally called the Technology Based Industry-University Committee, the coalition was assembled by the Industrial Development Division (IDD) of the University's Institute for Science and Technology for the purposes of expanding cooperation between industry and the University and promoting the development of technology-based industry in the Ann Arbor area.
With extensive staff support from the IDD, the steering committee for the autonomous Technology Based Industry-University Committee began holding monthly meetings in March 1979. In March 1981 the Committee renamed itself the Michigan Technology Council (MTC)and began expanding its scope to the regional and state level, becoming incorporated as a non-profit organization later that year. In 1983 the MTC outlined its newly defined mission: "to coordinate the initiatives of business leaders with those of all Michigan educational institutions, venture capital firms, Chambers of Commerce, industrial development groups, governmental units, and other groups whose goal is to create jobs in Michigan through the growth of technology-based businesses."
By 1986 MTC's membership had grown to include "over 1600 people from some 450 companies, educational institutions and governmental agencies throughout Michigan," most of whom were "middle and upper level managers." During the first decade of its existence, the MTC's major activities included holding forums such as breakfast briefings, conferences, and educational workshops; organizing job fairs and technology fairs; and establishing committees to research and promote Michigan technological growth in the specific areas of computers, robotics, biotechnology, and technology parks. At the time of this writing, MTC still exists as a statewide agency; its offices are located on the University of Michigan campus, and its main member services are specialty training seminars.
The records that make up the 1992 accession of the Michigan Technology Council record group document the founding and formative years of a broad-based Michigan organization concerned with an issue of vital concern to educational, business, and governmental leaders of the 1980s: the impact of high technology upon industry and society as a whole. Researchers interested in the changing nature of research and industry in the United States (and particularly in Michigan) during the technological boom of the 1980s will find in the record group ample accounts of such changes from the perspective of the people most interested in promoting them and profiting from them. Resistance to and fear of such changes are documented in the record group, as well, through letters and newspaper articles that present views opposing those of the MTC. The record group also provides insights about the relationships between industry, higher education, and government; particular technological topics such as computers, robotics, and biotechnology; tactics for promoting and marketing technological advances in various sectors of the community; and, of course, the history and organization of MTC itself.
Because the records of the 1992 accession were donated to the Bentley Historical Library not by the MTC but by a loosely related organization, the Industrial Development Division of the Institute for Science and Technology, and because the IDD's 1986 reorganization substantially diminished its connections to the MTC, the record group cannot provide a complete picture of the MTC; it documents the early rather than the recent history of the organization, and it concentrates heavily on a few MTC subcommittees and activities while providing scant details about others. Anticipated subsequent accessions to the record group should be able to fill in these gaps. Nevertheless, the records of the first accession document relatively comprehensively the organization's primary goals and concerns, as expressed through agendas, minutes, correspondence, reports, and pamphlets.
The records are organized into the following three series, reflecting their original order, which overlap each other considerably in terms of types of documents, subject matter, and chronology:
Topical Files, 1978-1988
Central Chronological Files, 1977-1987
Committee Files, 1968-1987
Subjects:
Michigan Technology Council.; University of Michigan. Institute of Science and Technology.; Ann Arbor Chamber of Commerce.; Research, Industrial--Michigan.; Science and Industry--Michigan.; Biotechnology--Research--Michigan.; Superior (Washtenaw County, Mich.: Township)
- Topical Files 1978-1988
  The Topical Files series is alphabetized according to type of document (e.g. By-laws, Correspondence) or subject matter (e.g. Background Research, Regional Divisions); documents within individual files are arranged chronologically.
  - Background Research 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Bylaws, 1980-1983 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1978-1988 (Box 1)
  - Leadership Lists (Board; Steering Committee, etc.), 1980-1987 (Box 1)
  - Membership Lists, Applications, etc. 1978-1983 (Box 1)
  - News Clippings, 1978-1987 (Box 1)
  - Organizational Charts and Policies, 1980-1984 (Box 1)
  - Profiles, Goals, and Strategies, 1981-1987 (Box 1)
  - Regional Divisions 1980-1985 (Box 1)
  - Related Organizations 1980-1985 (Box 1)
  - Reports, 1980-1983 (Box 1)
  - Tenth Anniversary 1988 (Box 1)
- Central Chronological Files 1977-1987
  The Central Chronological Files series consists primarily of minutes and agendas from meetings of the whole MTC and its central leadership, called variously the Executive Committee, Steering Committee, and Board of Directors. Interspersed chronologically with these documents are records such as correspondence, reports from committees, and newsletters.
  - 1977-1979 (Box 1)
  - 1980, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1981, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1982, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1983, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1984, 1985, 1987 (Box 1)
- Committee Files 1968-1987
  The Committee Files series is arranged alphabetically by committee.
  Of particular interest in the final series are the files concerning the Technology Park (Superior Township) Committee. The Technology Park Committee researched the possibility of attracting a large number of technology-based industries to the Ann Arbor area through the development of a commercial " technology park." Over a period of several years, the committee acquired grant money, evaluated sites, chose a site in Superior Township, and attempted to get such a technology park underway, alternately competing and cooperating with the developers of two similar parks in the area, eliciting alternately praise and condemnation from members of the community and the media. The Technology Park Committee developed a great degree of autonomy from MTC yet became closely intertwined with the Ypsilanti Chamber of Commerce and several other organizations. Although the Superior Township Technology Park never came into being, the Technology Park Committee files provides an insightful glimpse into the volatile interrelations among people of various backgrounds and interests that sprang up around high-technology issues.
  - General and Miscellaneous 1980-1982, undated (Box 2)
  - Biotechnology / Biomedical, 1982-1987, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Education
    - 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - 1982-1985, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Michigan Technology Fair, 1980-1985, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Technology Park (Superior Township)
    - Overviews and Organization 1981, undated (Box 2)
    - Agendas and Minutes (Steering Committee, Task Force, Executive Committee), 1980-1982 (Box 2)
    - Background Research 1968-1986 (Box 2)
    - Bendix Corporation (prospective technology park participant), 1980 (Box 2)
    - (Sub)Committees
      - Miscellaneous 1981 (Box 2)
      - Finance Committee, 1980-1982 (Box 2)
      - Option Committee, 1980-1982 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence
      - External 1980-1986 (Box 2)
      - Internal, including memos 1980-1983 (Box 2)
    - News Clippings, 1980-1983 (Box 2)
    - Proposals and Reports
      - Consultants and Contractors 1980-1982 (Box 2)
      - Technology Park Task Force, 1980-1983 (Box 2)
    - Related and Competing Technology Park Projects, 1982-1983 (Box 2)
    - Site Selection and Evaluation (includes blueprints and color photographs), 1981-1983 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous 1981-1983 (Box 2)
Related Material
Other collections at the Bentley Historical Library that relate to the MTC include the records of the University of Michigan Institute for Science and Technology and the Inventors' Council of Michigan.